Guide to the Physique Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Physique collection
1953-1997
MS 1850
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.67
(18 boxes)
The Physique Collection includes assorted publications that document changes in the codes, standards, and aesthetics of the male body.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Larry Kramer Initiative Executive Coordinator, 2004. Transferred from the Librarian for Gay and Lesbian Studies, 2007. Transferred from the Librarian for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Studies, 2015. Gift of Bert Hansen, 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by title.
Scope and Contents
The Physique Collection includes assorted publications that document changes in the codes, standards, and aesthetics of the male body.
Body image in men; Bodybuilding; Gay erotica; Homosexuality; LGBTQ resource
- Inventory, 1953-1997
  - Aces, nos. 1-2, undated (Box 1)
  - Adonis, vol. 1, no. 6, 1955 October (Box 1)
  - Advocate MEN
    - Vol. 1, nos. 1, 6; vol. 2, nos. 5, 11 [S/M], 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - No number [4 issues], 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Men of Advocate MEN, vol. 1, no 10; fragment, 1985 October-Nov, undated (Box 1)
  - L'Affaire, nos. 7-8, undated (Box 1)
  - The Al Parker Album, 1982 (Box 1)
  - All American Man, 1989 October (Box 1)
  - All-MAN, no. 6, 1988 October-November (Box 1)
  - American Centermen, no. 2, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Arena
    - No. 6, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Men of Arena, no. 1, 1978 October-December (Box 1)
  - Bear Magazine and/or influences [early issues; fragments], undated (Box 1)
  - Big
    - Annuals, vols. 2-5, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
    - The Big Boys, 2 issues, 1965 May, September (Box 1)
    - Monthly, vol. 3, no. 3; vol. 5, 1964 Jul, 1966 May (Box 1)
  - Bill the Hun [letter to "patron" regarding brochure], 1987 December 19 (Box 1)
  - Black is Bigger, vol. 1, no. 2, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Black Male, no. 2, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Blu, vol. 4, no. 1, undated (Box 1)
  - Blueboy
    - Vols. 8 [S/M], 11, 15, 20, 22, 28, 34, 40, 44, 50, 53, 61-62; vol. 10, no. 3, 1976-1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Fragments [from 8 issues], 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - America the Beautiful: The Official 1980 Blueboy Calendar (Box 2)
    - Blueboy Introduces Roger, undated (Box 2)
  - Body, vol. 8, no. 4, 1979 October-November (Box 2)
  - Body Beautiful, nos. 11, 15, 1960 October, 1961 October (Box 2)
  - Bronc, vol. 1, nos. 4, 8, 1982 Mar, 1983 February (Box 2)
  - Brothers Should Do It, vol. 1, no. 1, undated (Box 2)
  - Bruce of Los Angeles, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Butch, no. 3, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Can-Am Catalog and Video Reviews [gay wrestling videos], undated (Box 3)
  - Catalogues, undated (Box 3)
  - Cellblock, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Champ, vol. 2, no. 3, undated (Box 3)
  - "Chapter One" [writings-probably privately circulated], undated (Box 3)
  - Chico, no. 1, undated (Box 3)
  - Clothesdick, vol. 1, no. 6, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Colt
    - Calendar Men, issue 4 [S/M], 1994 (Box 4)
    - Calendars [S/M], 1984, 1990, 1992, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Catalogs, nos. 2-4, 1972-1973, undated (Box 4)
    - Colt Men, nos. 1, 8, 12, 19, 21, 1975-1989 (Box 4)
    - Colt Studio Presents, nos. 2-3, 1980, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Gallery
      - Nos. 2-4, 16, 1971, 1977, undated (Box 4)
      - The Best of Gallery, 2 issues including no. 2, 1974, undated (Box 4)
  - Dark Dudes, undated (Box 4)
  - David and his Friends, vols. 1, 3 [including David Goes Cowboy ], undated (Box 4)
  - The Dork, undated (Box 4)
  - Drum: Sex in Perspective, vol. 4, nos. 8, 10; vol. 5, nos. 1-2, 10-11, 1964-1966 (Box 4)
  - Dune, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Euros, nos. 19, 31, 35, 41, 1994-1997 (Box 4)
  - Falconers, no. 4, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Fizeek, nos. 5, 21, 29, 1960 Feb, 1963 Jun, 1964 October (Box 4)
  - Fizeek Art Quarterly, no. 7, undated (Box 4)
  - For Women Only, vol. 1, no. 2, 1979 spring (Box 4)
  - Foxhunt 7, 1988 (Box 4)
  - French, Jim, Men [calendar], 1994 (Box 13)
  - Gay Affair, undated (Box 4)
  - Gay Studs Annual, undated (Box 5)
  - Golden Boys, nos. 4-5, 9, 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Grecian Guild Studio Quarterly, no. 8, undated (Box 5)
  - Hard? A Pictorial and Literary Study, undated (Box 5)
  - Hard and Able, vol. 1, no. 1 [S/M], undated (Box 5)
  - Hard-on-Stage, vol. 1, no. 1 [S/M], 1984 (Box 5)
  - Heat, vol. 1, no. 4, 1988 January (Box 5)
  - Hechter, Conrad, calendar, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Hell's Angels [S/M], undated (Box 5)
  - Hermes, vol. 1, no. 1, undated (Box 5)
  - Hombre, no. 1, undated (Box 5)
  - Honcho [S/M], 13 issues including vol. 2, no. 15; vol. 4, nos. 14, 21; vol. 5, nos. 22, 24-25, 8-10; vol. 6, no. 3; vol. 7, no. 1; vol. 12, no. 1, 1979-1989 (Box 5)
  - How to Enlarge your Penis, 1970 (Box 5)
  - HUD, vol. 4, no. 3, undated (Box 5)
  - Hung Studs!, no. 1, undated (Box 5)
  - In Heat, no. 8, 1980 (Box 5)
  - In Touch [also known as In Touch for Men ], nos. 28, 49, 57-58, 63-64, 73, 1977-1982 (Box 5)
  - Inches
    - Vol. 1, nos. 2, 4, 6-8; vol. 2, nos. 2-5, 7, 9, 11-12; vol. 3, nos. 1, 3-7, 10-12; vol. 4, nos. 1, 3, 7, 9-10; vol. 5, nos. 2, 4, 6, 8, 10-11; vol. 6, no. 8, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
    - Men of Inches, vol. 1, no. 1, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Interracial illustrations [fragments from Stroke magazine], undated (Box 6)
  - J. Brian Presents Male Pix, no. 1, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Jacok in the Jungle, nos. 1, 3, undated (Box 6)
  - Javelin, no. 3, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Jean Paul, no. 35, 1988 September-November (Box 6)
  - John, undated (Box 6)
  - Johnny Harden and Friends, undated (Box 6)
  - Jr., no. 23, 1967 November (Box 6)
  - Kake, nos. 3 [2 versions], 5-6, 8, 10, 13, 22, undated (Box 7)
  - Lancer [S/M], 1979 (Box 7)
  - The Leathermen [S/M], 1978 (Box 7)
  - Let There Be Love, vol. 1, undated (Box 7)
  - Liquid Plumber, no. 6, undated (Box 7)
  - Loft: Best Designs for 1985, undated (Box 7)
  - Lover Boy, undated (Box 7)
  - Mach Quarterly, vol. 1, no. 1, undated (Box 7)
  - Male, no. 5, 1979 July (Box 7)
  - Male Classics Annual, 2 issues, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - The Male European Nudist, no. 4, 1966 (Box 7)
  - The Male Figure, vols. 14, 20, 33 [Bruce of Los Angeles], undated (Box 7)
  - Male Nudist Physique, no. 3, undated (Box 7)
  - Male Pictorial, 2 issues, 1991 Apr, 1992 March (Box 7)
  - Mandate
    - Vol. 4, no. 47; vol. 5, nos. 48, 50, 54-55; vol. 8, nos. 74, 78-79; vol. 9, no. 86; vol. 10, nos. 1, 4, 10, 12, 1979-1985 (Box 7)
    - Fragments, 1981 Jan, Oct, 1982 March (Box 7)
    - Christmas 1979 centerfold [poster] (Box 7)
  - Manifest, vol. 5, no. 14, 1983 July (Box 8)
  - MAN-ifique!, no. 6, 1957 December (Box 8)
  - Manpower! [Colt Studios publication], nos. 1, 3 [S/M-2 versions], 4 [S/M], 6 [S/M], 8, 1969-1975 (Box 8)
  - MANual, vol. 1, no. 3; nos. 22, 34, 52, 72, 1959-1966 (Box 8)
  - Mars, no. 17, 1966 January (Box 8)
  - Meat-Rack, vol. 1, no. 1, undated (Box 8)
  - Meet West. Just one of THE BIG 100!, undated (Box 13)
  - Men of Locker, no. 1 [S/M], 1979 May-July (Box 8)
  - Mentor
    - No. 2, 1979 January-March (Box 8)
    - Collector's edition, undated (Box 8)
  - Midnite Cowboys, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Mondo Taurus, no. 1, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Motorcyclist" [writings with accompanying illustrations-probably privately circulated], undated (Box 8)
  - Mr. Sun, vol. 1, no. 5 [fragment], undated (Box 8)
  - Muscleboy, vol. 1, no. 6, 1964 April-May (Box 8)
  - 199? [calendar], undated (Box 8)
  - Numbers
    - 12 issues including vols. 3, 49, 52, 54, 69, 70, 1977-1984 (Box 8)
    - Annual, vol. 4, no. 4, 1980 spring-summer (Box 8)
  - 199? [calendar], undated (Box 9)
  - Olympus [Colt Studios publication], vol. 1, no. 1, 1972 (Box 9)
  - 100 Numbers Presents Action Shots of the Hotline Series, vol. 1, no. 4, undated (Box 9)
  - Paean, no. 3, 1979 (Box 9)
  - The Photographers' Guild, Catalog A, undated (Box 9)
  - Physical Man, no. 3, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Physique Pictorial
    - Vol. 4, no. 1-vol. 6, no. 3; vol. 7, no. 1-vol. 14, no. 3; vol. 15, nos. 1-2, 4; vol. 16, nos. 1, 4; vol. 24-26, 36, 40, 1954-1967 (Box 9)
    - Physique: A Pictorial History of the Athletic Model Guild, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Playgirl, vol. 2, no. 6, 1974 November (Box 9)
  - Playguy, vol. 1, no. 6; vol. 4, nos. 1-2; vol. 6, nos. 11-12; vol. 9, no. 6, 1985 Jun, undated (Box 9)
  - Popular Man, 1957 November (Box 9)
  - Private Males, vol. 1, no. 1, undated (Box 9)
  - Quaintance: clippings [fragments], 1972, undated (Box 9)
  - Quaintance followers: clippings [fragments], undated (Box 9)
  - QQ Magazine, vol. 8, no. 5, 1976 September-October (Box 9)
  - Rammer, no. 1, undated (Box 9)
  - Raunch!, undated (Box 9)
  - Rocco, Pat, catalog of male films, photos, color slides, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Rogues' Gallery, no. 1, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Ski Summit: The Other Side of Aspen, Part 1, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Skin, vol. 2, no. 2; vol. 3, no. 6; vol. 4, no. 1; vol. 5, no. 1, 1980-1983 (Box 10)
  - Skinflicks, vol. 3, no. 4, 1983 (Box 10)
  - Sling, no. 1 [S/M], 1979 (Box 10)
  - Solo, no. 1, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Spike Team, vol. 1, no. 1, 1979 May (Box 10)
  - Spurs [Colt Studios publication], nos. 7-8, 10 [S/M], 20, 1982-1992 (Box 10)
  - ST Men, vol. 2, undated (Box 10)
  - Strap, no. 3 [S/M], 1979 (Box 10)
  - Stroke, vol. 1, no. 1, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Strokes, no. 1, 1979 (Box 10)
  - Take Off, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Ten Inch Tools [S/M], undated (Box 11)
  - 321 Guys, vol. 1, no. 1, 1974 July-September (Box 11)
  - Tiny Tim, vol. 2, undated (Box 11)
  - Together, 1976 (Box 11)
  - Tom of Finland
    - Beach Boys, no. 1, undated (Box 11)
    - The Best of Tom of Finland, undated (Box 11)
    - Catalog, undated (Box 11)
    - Clippings, 1979, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 11)
    - Circus, undated (Box 11)
    - The First Tom of Finland Calendar, 1978 (Box 11)
    - Greeting card [with note], 1990 (Box 11)
    - Retrospective [inscribed], 1988 (Box 11)
    - Retrospective II, 1991 (Box 11)
    - Sex in the Shed, undated (Box 11)
  - Tomorrow's Man, vol. 1, nos. 6-8, 10; vol. 2, nos. 1, 7, 11; vol. 3, nos. 5, 3, 5, 12; vol. 4, no. 2; vol. 6, no. 3; vol. 7, no. 9; vol. 8, no. 3; vol. 10, nos. 11-12; vol. 13, no. 4, 1953-1965 (Box 11)
  - Topman, vol. 1, no. 45, 1981 February 16 (Box 11)
  - Torso, vol. 1, nos. 9, 12; vol. 2, nos. 2, 8; vol. 5, no. 6; vol. 7, no. 4; vol. 8, no. 8, 1983-1990 (Box 11)
  - Trim
    - Nos. 9, 20, 49, 1958 Nov, 1960 Nov, 1966 April (Box 12)
    - Trim Studio Quarterly, no. 17, 1966 spring (Box 12)
  - Undergear, 1989 summer (Box 12)
  - Urge, no. 2, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Vim, 6 issues including vol. 11, no. 2; vol. 3, no. 4; vol. 4, no. 12; vol. 7, no. 1, 1955-1965, undated (Box 12)
  - Young and Eager, no. 1, undated (Box 12)
  - Young Guys!, no. 17, 1968 June (Box 12)
  - The Young Physique, 2 issues including vol. 2, no. 3, 1960 Aug, undated (Box 12)
  - The Zeus Collection
    - Cavelo [S/M], 1980 (Box 12)
    - Cowboys, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, undated (Box 12)
- Additional Material, 1976, 1996; Accession 2007-M-074
  - Lüger [premier collectors edition of drawings by Lüger], undated (Box 1)
  - Männespielen: A Portfolio of Drawings by Rex [first publication], 1976 March (Box 1)
  - 100 Male Nudes: The Best of Physique Pictorial [mini-book of photographs and drawings that appeared in Physique Pictorial, a publication in existence from 1952-1993], 1996 (Box 1)
- Additional material, Circa 1955-circa 1965; Accession 2015-M-075
  Scope and Contents
  This accession comprises items of promotional ephemera for Champion Studios and other Physique Magazine photography and art producers. Most of the items are order forms for different art and photographic prints.
  - Promotional ephemera, Circa 1955-circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1954-1974; Accession 2018-M-0007
  - American Apollo, 2nd issue, 1959; Lacks back cover. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Physique, 1:2, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art & Physique (2 issues), Summer 1957, Fall 1957, 1960; 1960; 1960 issue lacks front cover. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Big Boys, 1965-07 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dandy Lions, number 2, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fizeek, number 1, 1959-05; Lacks front cover. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Grecian Guild Pictorial, Winter 1955 and December 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grecian Guild Studio Quarterly, number 18, Summer 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gymn, The Magazine of Male Athletes, number 3, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lon Connoisseur Album, number 2, 1957-01 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Male Classics, Autumn 1958, Summer 1959, Fall 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Male Figure, Winter 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Male Form, number 9, undated issue, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Male Model Parade (photographs by Lon), numbers 3, 4, 6, 1957, 1958, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Male Pix (photographs by Lon), volumes 1, 2, 3, and 4, 1957, 1958, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Male Pose, numbers 7, 8, and 15, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Male Power, 50cents, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Man Alive, numbers 3, 5, and two unidentified issues, January 1959, June-July 1959; 2 issues lack front covers. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Manhattan Man 1:1, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Man-ifique, 1957-03 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Manorama (bi-monthly Washington, D. C.), 1961; Lacks front and back covers. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Man's World, April 1956, February 1959; 1959-02 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Manual, numbers 7, 69, and 82, October 1959, October 1965, February 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mars, numbers 3 and 19, September 1963, May 1966; 1966-05 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Men and Art, numbers 1, 4, 5, 8, and 9, 1954, 1955, 1958, 1959; Number 8 lacks back cover. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Modern Adonis, number 23, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Physique Artistry, numbers 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, and 18, Summer 1957, Autumn 1957, Winter 1958, Spring 1958, Summer 1958, Autumn 1958, Winter 1959, Spring 1959, Winter 1960; Number 18 is incomplete. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Physique Photos, number 1, Circa 1954-1974; Lacks back cover. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Physique Pictorial, 4:3, 5:1, 7:2, 8:1, 8:3, 9:1, 9:3, 26, and three unidentified issues, Fall 1954, Spring 1955, Summer 1957, Spring 1958, Fall 1958, Spring 1959, January 1960, December 1974; 8 issues have missing pages. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Physique World, numbers 2 and 6, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Popular Man, January 1958, March 1959; 1959-03 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Portfolio 1: Photographer's Choice, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Star Models, numbers 4 and 5, 1956, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tiger, numbers 1 and 3, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Today's Male, Circa 1954-1974; Missing 3 pages. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Today's Man, volume 2, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tomorrow's Man (three formats), 2 small issues, 3 medium, 6 large, August 1953, September 1953, October 1955, January 1956, July 1956, January 1958, July 1958, March 1959, April 1959, March 1960, September 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trim 54, 2 issues, February 1967, Circa 1954-1974; Second issue lacks front cover. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Trim Studio Quarterly, number 5, Circa 1954-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vim, 2:6, 2:9, 5:5, August 1955, November 1955, probably May 1958; All three issues lack front covers. (Box 3, Folder 4)